<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<data>
	<node>
		<id><![CDATA[13]]></id>
		<link><![CDATA[https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/story/13]]></link>
		<title><![CDATA[The Final Chapter in the Hunt for Bin Ladin]]></title>
		<details><![CDATA[Abbottabad, Pakistan—In the early morning hours of May 2, 2011, a US military raid on an al-Qa‘ida compound killed Usama Bin Ladin, America’s most wanted terrorist.  The mission’s success was the culmination of many years of complex, thorough, and highly advanced intelligence operations and analyses led by the CIA with support from partners across the Intelligence Community.

Shortly after the 9/11 terrorist attacks on the United States, the CIA began collecting information on key individuals connected to or providing support to Bin Ladin.  Reporting made clear early on that he communicated via a network of couriers.  It was years later, however, before more was known about one key courier than simply his kunya, or operational pseudonym.  Analysts then worked several more years before identifying the area in Pakistan where the courier was believed to be located.

By late 2010, further intelligence enabled the identification of the courier's compound in Abbottabad, a town in Pakistan’s Khyber-Pakhtunkhwa Province (formerly the Northwest Frontier Province), about 35 miles north of Islamabad.  The compound and its main residence had extensive security features unusual for the area:  high walls topped with barbed wire, double entry gates, opaque windows, no apparent internet or telephone connections, and all trash burned rather than collected.  Moreover, the two registered owners did not appear to work or have an income that would allow them to afford such a large residence.  This led the Intelligence Community to assess that the compound was probably being used to hide Bin Ladin, as well as the courier.

The operation on May 2nd, authorized by the President on April 29th, was a surgical raid by a small team of special operations forces designed to minimize collateral damage and to pose as little risk as possible to noncombatants on the compound or to Pakistani civilians in the neighborhood.  In the aftermath, Bin Ladin was positively identified via several independent means.

The large quantity of materials collected from the compound required time for a thorough review.  The CIA led a multi-agency task force to prioritize, catalogue, and analyze them for intelligence about al-Qa‘ida’s affiliates, plans and intentions, and current threats.  The collected materials indicated that Bin Ladin remained an active leader in al-Qa‘ida, providing strategic, operational, and tactical instructions to the organization.  Though separated from many al-Qa‘ida members in remote areas of the region, he was far from a figurehead.  Bin Ladin remained in charge while in hiding.

Bin Ladin was al-Qa‘ida’s founder and only amir, or commander, in its history until his death.  He was largely responsible for the organization’s mystique, its ability to raise money and attract new recruits, and its focus on the United States as a target for terrorist attacks.  The death of Usama Bin Ladin marked a significant victory in the US-led campaign to disrupt, dismantle, and defeat al-Qa‘ida.

The daring raid that ensured that Bin Ladin will never kill again was a team effort, the product of increased integration within the Intelligence Community and of close collaboration with our military partners.  The CIA was at the center of it all, driving the collection of vital information, assessing each piece of data, and analyzing all sources to produce the compelling intelligence case that led US forces to Abbottabad.  The Agency's contributions were the product of a decade of positive changes -- improved collection, analysis, technology, and support.]]></details>
		<relatedartifacts><![CDATA[Al-Qa’ida Training Manual
Al-Qa’ida Gas Mask
Model of Abbottabad Compound
Brick from Abbottabad Compound]]></relatedartifacts>
		<relatedartifactslinks><![CDATA[https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/47

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/48

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/226

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/227]]></relatedartifactslinks>
		<videos><![CDATA[]]></videos>
	</node>
	<node>
		<id><![CDATA[6]]></id>
		<link><![CDATA[https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/story/6]]></link>
		<title><![CDATA[On the Front Lines: CIA in Afghanistan]]></title>
		<details><![CDATA[In the aftermath of the tragic terrorist attacks of September 11, 2001, President George W. Bush ordered Director of Central Intelligence George Tenet to launch operations against the al-Qa‘ida terrorist organization and its Taliban supporters in Afghanistan.  This order called for the CIA to collect real-time, actionable intelligence to help shape the battlefield and to use all means to target al-Qa‘ida.  Within 15 days of the attacks on US soil, the first team of CIA officers was on the ground and operating in Afghanistan—some 8,000 miles from home.

This rapid deployment was possible because the CIA had developed and nurtured relationships with the Afghan Northern Alliance for several years prior to 9/11.  Because of this thorough, low-key, and persistent effort, CIA officers knew the language, the history, and the culture of the region and were in position to move quickly against the terrorists. In addition to being “first on the ground” in October 2001, the CIA team was able to quickly amass an enormous body of information and a large stable of assets to launch rapid and robust efforts against the Taliban.

As the weeks unfolded, a core group of more than 100 CIA officers— primarily operations and paramilitary officers as well as officers from the Directorate of Support, all highly experienced leaders known for their independence, skill, initiative, and bravery—worked with some 300 US Special Forces personnel and partnered with local tribal and military forces.  Team members took risks and worked with key groups in the area, doing whatever was necessary to accomplish the mission.

All-source intelligence enhanced the operations. The networks of sources that the CIA had developed in Afghanistan over the previous two decades provided critical information on the enemy’s capabilities, plans, intentions, and motivations.  The overall success of military operations in those first few months is well-documented.  Aided by superior firepower and backed every step of the way by a dedicated team of intelligence professionals, the United States and allied forces made significant strides in those early months.  Outside Afghanistan, CIA teams with officers representing all Agency directorates supported officers in the field.

The combined efforts of the US Intelligence Community, the US military, Afghan allies, and coalition partners led to swift success.  By early December 2001—in less than three months—the Taliban regime had been overthrown, a significant number of the al-Qa’ida leadership had been killed or captured, and a major terrorist safe haven had been eliminated.  Through it all, the CIA’s integrated intelligence collection, communications, technology, logistics, and delegated leadership were invaluable to the campaign.

Most importantly for the Agency, the lessons learned in those early days of the war against al-Qa‘ida—and in the years since—have become part of the CIA’s fabric.  We are more agile, adaptive, and collaborative.  More than half of our workforce has been hired since 9/11, and integration—internally among our Directorates and externally with our Intelligence Community, military, and other partners—is considered a key component of any Agency success.  These changes—developed in part from the war in Afghanistan and the war against al-Qa‘ida—will certainly pass the test of time and are already providing a strong base for our future.]]></details>
		<relatedartifacts><![CDATA[Al-Qa’ida Training Manual
Al-Qa’ida Gas Mask
Lapis Lazuli
Blood Chit
Special Operations Forces Laser Marker (SOFLAM)
Shrade Tool
Mine Probing Tool
Admiral Calland’s Desert Combat Uniform Top
Afghan Hat
PRC-112B1 Survival Radio
Pointy-Talky Language Chart
Escape & Evasion Survival Kit
Afghan Saddle
Cast of a Few, Courage of a Nation
US Army Lensatic Compass
Operation JAWBREAKER Knife
Mi-17 Helicopter Clock
Holy Bible Used in a Memorial Service Honoring Mike Spann
Moleskin Notebook
Piece of the Wing Section from a Mi-17 Helicopter]]></relatedartifacts>
		<relatedartifactslinks><![CDATA[https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/47

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/48

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/49

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/50

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/52

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/53

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/54

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/55

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/56

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/57

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/58

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/59

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/62

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/113

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/119

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/170

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/171

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/172

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/173

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/174

]]></relatedartifactslinks>
		<videos><![CDATA[]]></videos>
	</node>
	<node>
		<id><![CDATA[10]]></id>
		<link><![CDATA[https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/story/10]]></link>
		<title><![CDATA[CIA's Impact on Technology]]></title>
		<details><![CDATA[Virtually any job you can imagine is available at the CIA.  In addition to the more well-known jobs of analyst or core collector, the Agency needs medical professionals, IT specialists, graphics artists, and other skilled personnel--even sometimes hair stylists, carpenters, and seamstresses--to accomplish its mission of protecting the national security of the United States.  Because of the need to work in somewhat of an independent environment, the CIA must sometimes develop technologies to meet the unique requirements of its officers.  With this in mind, you might not be surprised to learn that, after a declassification process, publicly released technologies developed by CIA have gone on to impact the world in positive ways.

One of CIA's best examples of such technology may hit closer to home than you'd think—the lithium-iodine battery.  Developed in the 1960s by CIA to solve the problems of varying reliability and short lifespan of batteries, the lithium-iodine battery improved the performance of surveillance equipment and prolonged the operation of reconnaissance satellites.  In the modern sense, the benefits of this declassified technology can be felt all the way from professional arenas such as, the medical community's use of it in pacemakers, to less-formal arenas like powering your cell phone or digital camera.

The medical community often benefits from research and development performed by the CIA and other Intelligence Community organizations.  For example, to assist radiologists in detecting breast cancer, CIA provided technology originally developed for the analysis of satellite imagery.  Specifically, the technique involved aligning and comparing digital x-ray images taken over time to identify any changes.  These results were particularly helpful in diagnosing breast cancer in women under 50, where diagnosis is particularly difficult.  The use of these methods is believed to have considerably reduced the number of deaths from breast cancer.

CIA developed the Identi-Kit to assist in sketching the face of a person of interest based upon witness recollections. The kit breaks a full-face image into component parts—hair, brows, eyes, nose, lips, chin-line with ears, and age lines, plus beard, hat, and glasses, if any. It contains several dozen transparent slides picturing each of these components with different types of contours, 500 slides in all, with five notches on the side for different placements of each feature. From the kit’s catalog of slides, a witness selects those that best portray the subject person’s facial characteristics. The resulting image is not a finished portrait but a reasonably good line-drawing of distinctive physical contours.  A key benefit of the kit is the ease with which it permits a sketch to be sent quickly via telephone using only slide codes that enable reconstruction of the sketch with another kit.  The kit also provides a standardized set of facial descriptors that may be used in identifying a wide spectrum of individuals.  After intelligence officers thoroughly proved Identi-Kit’s utility in many real-life operations over recent years, CIA released it to police forces for use in apprehending criminals.

A non-traditional way that CIA has helped make a significant impact on the world is through one of its former employees.  Robert Barron, a currently certified clinical anaplastologist, honed much of his natural artistic talents during his work as a CIA disguise specialist.  Having retired from CIA in 1993, Barron now works with medically disfigured patients to improve their confidence and restore their sense of identity by designing prosthetics tailored specifically for each patient.  Barron credits his time at the CIA as the foundation for his second career, stating, “my work with disguises is what led me to where I am now.”  He further explained that each operational disguise piece he created at CIA was “unique and demanded creativity,” much like the prosthetics he currently designs.  If you are interested in reading more about Barron, click here to access a previously featured article about him.

Finally, the CIA-assisted technology probably most familiar to you is one many of us use on a regular basis:  Google Earth.  In February 2003, the CIA-funded venture-capitalist firm In-Q-Tel made a strategic investment in Keyhole, Inc., a pioneer of interactive 3-D earth visualization and creator of the groundbreaking rich-mapping EarthViewer 3D system.  CIA worked closely with other Intelligence Community organizations to tailor Keyhole’s systems to meet their needs.  The finished product transformed the way intelligence officers interacted with geographic information and earth imagery.  Users could now easily combine complicated sets of data and imagery into clear, realistic visual representations.  Users could “fly” from space to street level seamlessly while interactively exploring layers of information including roads, schools, businesses, and demographics.  In the private sector, this flyover capability was so compelling that multiple TV networks used EarthViewer 3D to fly over Iraqi cities and landscapes in news broadcasts using publicly available satellite images.  All of this acclaim eventually caught the attention of Google Inc., a multinational cyber-focused corporation, which acquired Keyhole in 2004, thereby laying the groundwork for the development of Google Earth.

So the next time you are exploring a new land from the comfort of your laptop or snapping pictures with your lithium-battery-powered digital camera, take a moment to think about some other ways CIA technology may have improved life outside its walls.]]></details>
		<relatedartifacts><![CDATA[Digital X-Ray Detector Panel
Lithium-Iodine Battery]]></relatedartifacts>
		<relatedartifactslinks><![CDATA[https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/13

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/15]]></relatedartifactslinks>
		<videos><![CDATA[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XTCoOKZoDIE&feature=emb_logo]]></videos>
	</node>
	<node>
		<id><![CDATA[12]]></id>
		<link><![CDATA[https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/story/12]]></link>
		<title><![CDATA[Terrorist Bombing of Pan Am Flight 103]]></title>
		<details><![CDATA[On 21 December 1988, Pan American flight 103, a Boeing 747, took off from London, bound for New York City.  As it was climbing on its northerly flight path, it exploded over the town of Lockerbie in the Dumfries and Galloway region of southwest Scotland.  In all, 270 people from 21 countries were killed, including all 259 passengers and crewmembers plus 11 people on the ground in Lockerbie.

The plastic explosive that detonated in the forward cargo hold triggered a sequence of events that led to the rapid destruction of the aircraft.  Winds scattered victims and debris along an 81-mile-long corridor 845 square miles in area.

The Lockerbie bombing became the subject of Britain's largest criminal inquiry led by its smallest police force, the Dumfries and Galloway Constabulary.  This widely regarded assault on a symbol of the United States, with 189 of the victims being Americans, stood as the deadliest terrorist attack on American civilians until the attacks of September 11, 2001.

The determined investigation over more than 11 years was a jigsaw-puzzle assembly by many cooperating law-enforcement, intelligence, and legal personnel from numerous countries—including a CIA electronics expert who uncovered a key piece of evidence.

In 1989, months after the plane crash and end of the formal recovery effort, a piece of scorched shirt was discovered.  The piece contained a fragment of circuit board that the heat of the explosion had fused into the shirt’s polyester fabric.

The Scots photographed the circuit-board fragment and gave a photo to the FBI, who passed a copy to the CIA where a Directorate of Science & Technology (DS&T) electronics expert observed two things that reminded him of a device he had seen before—a timer from an earlier Libyan terrorist attack.  Further analysis confirmed that the fragment exactly matched part of a timer circuit manufactured specifically for the Libyans.

The trial of two Libyans convened before a Scottish court in the Netherlands in 2000.  CIA’s DS&T officer was called to the stand as an expert witness.  To protect his identity he was in disguise, used an alias, and had his voice altered.  The CIA officer differentiated the timers of the Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine-General Command (PFLP-GC) from the ones used by the Libyans and identified the circuit-board fragment to be from a Libyan timer.  These facts were crucial because the Libyans’ defense rested on the premise that the PFLP-GC—not the Libyans—had bombed Pan Am 103.

Terrorists have always operated in secrecy, in part because America and its allies devote advanced technical resources to uncovering and thwarting their plans.  While technical experts called in after a terrorist incident provide valuable assistance to those who seek justice, CIA experts in weapons, ordnance, electronics, and other fields work in the shadows to prevent such incidents.  As a matter of pride to these experts who are accustomed to anonymity, few people know the details of their lifesaving contributions to combating terrorism.

In the case of Pan Am 103, the CIA expert’s testimony on his identification of the circuit-board fragment was key evidence that led to the conviction of one of the two accused Libyan terrorists.]]></details>
		<relatedartifacts><![CDATA[Pan Am 103 Lapel Pin]]></relatedartifacts>
		<relatedartifactslinks><![CDATA[https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/120]]></relatedartifactslinks>
		<videos><![CDATA[]]></videos>
	</node>
	<node>
		<id><![CDATA[8]]></id>
		<link><![CDATA[https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/story/8]]></link>
		<title><![CDATA[Rescue of the “Canadian Six” — A Classic Case of Deception]]></title>
		<details><![CDATA[Few CIA counterterrorist successes have ever been made public.  Described here is one of them, a classic case of deception in which CIA technical specialists created a dummy movie-production company in Hollywood and delivered disguises and documents that made possible the escape of six US diplomats from capture in Iran in 1980.  The CIA closely held the story until revealing it to the public for the Agency’s 50th anniversary celebration in 1997.

On 4 November 1979, militant Islamic students took over the US Embassy in Tehran, Iran, and took hostage the 66 US personnel inside.  Avoiding capture that day were six US State Department employees who took refuge in the homes of Canadian Embassy officers.  The US Government developed several major operations to address this national crisis.  Among them was a scheme developed by a small team of CIA disguise and false-documentation specialists to exfiltrate the “Canadian Six” (as they became known) from the country.

The exfiltration task was daunting—the six Americans had no intelligence background; planning required extensive coordination within the US and Canadian governments; and failure not only threatened the safety of the hostages but also posed considerable risk of worldwide embarrassment to the US and Canada.  Other significant problems included overcoming Iran’s strict immigration exit controls and creation of a credible cover story and supporting documentation for the six Americans.

After careful consideration of numerous options, the chosen plan began to take shape.  Canadian Parliament agreed to grant Canadian passports to the six Americans.  The CIA team together with an experienced motion-picture consultant devised a cover story so exotic that it would not likely draw suspicions—the production of a Hollywood movie.

The team set up a dummy company, “Studio Six Productions,” with offices on the old Columbia Studio lot formerly occupied by Michael Douglas, who had just completed producing The China Syndrome.  This upstart company titled its new production “Argo” after the ship that Jason and the Argonauts sailed in rescuing the Golden Fleece from the many-headed dragon holding it captive in the sacred garden—much like the situation in Iran.  The script had a Middle Eastern sci-fi theme that glorified Islam.  The story line was intentionally complicated and difficult to decipher.  Ads proclaimed Argo to be a “cosmic conflagration” written by Teresa Harris (the alias selected for one of the six awaiting exfiltration).

President Jimmy Carter approved the rescue operation.  The CIA team prepared for the newly christened “movie-production crew” forged documentation and disguise packages to be shipped via diplomatic pouch to the Canadian Embassy in Tehran.  CIA specialists—under the guise of a Studio Six Productions team scouting for a suitable filming location in Tehran—traveled to Iran to complete necessary travel documents and make final arrangements with the six Americans and their Canadian hosts.

The day before their departure, the six Americans rehearsed their cover stories and movie-production roles.  Their new images included disguises and wardrobes with a “Hollywood” flare—tight trousers, silk shirt unbuttoned down the front with chest hair cradling a gold chain and medallion for one man.  Policymakers back home were pleased with the plan, signing off their final cable, “See you later, exfiltrator!”

Traveling through Tehran’s Mehrabad Airport was typically chaotic, clogged with traveler traffic on top of overzealous customs and immigration officials and roving Revolutionary Guards.  An early morning flight had been picked to increase the chances of a smooth departure—officials would be sleepy, Revolutionary Guards would be in bed, and travelers would be at a minimum.  The six Americans and their CIA-escort “production manager” passed through customs and immigration without a hitch.  After an hour delay due to a minor mechanical problem, the flight—with its fake movie crew aboard—was in the air and headed for Zurich.  A collective sigh of relief came over the Americans when the plane cleared Iranian airspace.

News of the escape and Canada’s role quickly broke.  Americans went wild in celebrating their appreciation to Canada and its Embassy staff.  The maple leaf flew in a hundred cities and towns across the US.  Billboards exclaimed “Thank you Canada!”  Full-page newspaper ads expressed American’s thanks to its neighbors to the north.  Thirty-thousand baseball fans cheered Canada’s Ambassador to Iran and the six rescued Americans, honored guests at a game in Yankee Stadium.

Studio Six Productions soon folded, the public unaware of CIA’s role in orchestrating this most successful rescue operation.]]></details>
		<relatedartifacts><![CDATA["Studio Six Productions" Accoutrements

Argo Ads and Articles in Variety

“Studio Six Productions” Logo Items

Artist’s Concepts for Argo

“Studio Six Productions” Portfolio

Argo Producer Notes]]></relatedartifacts>
		<relatedartifactslinks><![CDATA[https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/122

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/147

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/148

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/149

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/150

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/151]]></relatedartifactslinks>
		<videos><![CDATA[]]></videos>
	</node>
	<node>
		<id><![CDATA[14]]></id>
		<link><![CDATA[https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/story/14]]></link>
		<title><![CDATA[Project AZORIAN]]></title>
		<details><![CDATA[Imagine standing atop the Empire State Building with an 8-foot-wide grappling hook on a 1-inch-diameter steel rope.  Your task is to lower the hook to the street below, snag a compact car full of gold, and lift the car back to the top of the building.  On top of that, the job has to be done without anyone noticing.  That, essentially, describes what the CIA did in Project AZORIAN, a highly secret six-year effort to retrieve a sunken Soviet submarine from the Pacific Ocean floor during the Cold War.

The story began in 1968 when K-129, a Soviet Golf II-class submarine carrying three SS-N-4 nuclear-armed ballistic missiles, sailed from the naval base at Petropavlovsk on Russia’s Kamchatka Peninsula to take up its peacetime patrol station in the Pacific Ocean northeast of Hawaii.  Soon after leaving port, the submarine and its entire crew were lost.  After the Soviets abandoned their extensive search efforts, the US located the submarine about 1,800 miles northwest of Hawaii on the ocean floor 16,500 feet below.  Recognizing the immense value of the intelligence on Soviet strategic capabilities that would be gained if the submarine were recovered, the CIA agreed to lead such a recovery effort with support from the Department of Defense.

CIA engineers faced a daunting task:  lift the huge 1,750-ton, 132-foot-long portion of the wrecked submarine from an ocean abyss more than three miles below—under total secrecy.

In 1970, after careful study, a team of CIA engineers and contractors determined that the only technically feasible approach was to use a large mechanical claw to grasp the hull and a heavy-duty hydraulic system mounted on a surface ship to lift it.

The ship would be called the Hughes Glomar Explorer, ostensibly a commercial deep-sea mining vessel ostensibly built and owned by billionaire Howard Hughes, who provided the plausible cover story that his ship was conducting marine research at extreme ocean depths and mining manganese nodules lying on the sea bottom.  The ship would have the requisite stability and power to perform the task at hand.

Constructed over the next four years, the ship included a derrick similar to an oil-drilling rig, a pipe-transfer crane, two tall docking legs, a huge claw-like capture vehicle, a center docking well (called the “moon pool”) large enough to contain the hoisted portion of the sub, and doors to open and close the well’s floor.  To preserve the mission’s secrecy, the capture vehicle was built under roof and loaded into the ship from a barge submerged underneath.  With these special capabilities, the ship could conduct the entire recovery under water, away from the view of other ships, aircraft, or spy satellites.

The heavy-lift operation was complex and fraught with risk.  While maintaining its position in the ocean currents, the ship had to lower the capture vehicle by adding 60-foot sections of supporting steel pipe, one at a time.  When it reached the submarine section, the capture vehicle then had to be positioned to straddle the sunken submarine section, and its powerful jaws had to grab the hull.  Then the ship had to raise the capture vehicle with the section in its clutches by reversing the lift process and removing supporting pipe sections one at a time until the submarine was securely stowed in the ship’s docking well.

Sailing from Long Beach, California, the Glomar Explorer arrived over the recovery site on 4 July 1974 and conducted salvage operations for more than two months under total secrecy—despite much of the time being monitored by nearby Soviet ships curious about its mission.  The crew encountered many problems, some serious, but quickly overcame them, and the lift proceeded according to plan.  However, when the submarine section was about halfway up, it broke apart, and a portion plunged back to the ocean bottom.  Crestfallen, the Glomar crew successfully hauled up the portion that remained in the capture vehicle.

Among the contents of the recovered section were the bodies of six Soviet submariners.  They were given a formal military burial at sea.  In a gesture of good will, Director of Central Intelligence Robert Gates presented a film of the burial ceremony to Russian President Boris Yeltsin in 1992.

Almost immediately after the disappointing recovery effort, planning began for a second mission to recover the lost portion.  A bizarre and totally unforeseen occurrence, however, had already started a chain of events that would ultimately expose the Glomar Explorer’s true purpose and make another mission impossible.  In June 1974, just before the Glomar set sail, thieves had broken into one of the Hughes offices in Los Angeles and stolen secret documents, one tying Howard Hughes to CIA and the Glomar Explorer.  Desperate to recover this document, CIA called in the FBI, which in turn enlisted the Los Angeles Police Department.  The search drew attention, and by the autumn of 1974 the media began to pick up rumors of a sensational story.

Director of Central Intelligence William E. Colby personally appealed to those who had learned about AZORIAN not to disclose the project.  For a while they cooperated, but on 7 February 1975 the Los Angeles Times published an account that made connections between the robbery, Hughes, CIA, and the recovery operation.  After that, investigative reporter Jack Anderson broke the story on national television, asserting that Navy experts had told him the sunken submarine contained no real secrets and that the project was a waste of taxpayers' money.  Journalists flooded into the Long Beach area where the Glomar was preparing for its second mission.  The Ford Administration neither confirmed nor denied any of the stories in circulation, but by late June, the Soviets had assigned a ship to monitor and guard the recovery site.  With Glomar’s cover blown, the White House canceled further recovery operations.

The Glomar's brief covert career was now over, and after some experimental ocean mining voyages sponsored by a consortium of industry leaders, it was mothballed for over a quarter century.  Then in the late 1990s, a US petroleum company restored the ship for use in deep-sea oil drilling and exploration.  Renamed the GSF Explorer, the ship is still being used for that purpose.

Although Project AZORIAN failed to meet its full intelligence objectives, CIA considered the operation to be one of the greatest intelligence coups of the Cold War.  Project AZORIAN remains an engineering marvel, advancing the state of the art in deep-ocean mining and heavy-lift technology.]]></details>
		<relatedartifacts><![CDATA[Manganese Nodule Encased in Lucite

Glomar Explorer Bunk Card

Flag that Flew Above the Glomar Explorer

Glomar Explorer Crew Patch]]></relatedartifacts>
		<relatedartifactslinks><![CDATA[https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/192

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/193

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/194

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/195]]></relatedartifactslinks>
		<videos><![CDATA[]]></videos>
	</node>
	<node>
		<id><![CDATA[5]]></id>
		<link><![CDATA[https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/story/5]]></link>
		<title><![CDATA[A-12 OXCART]]></title>
		<details><![CDATA[CIA developed the highly secret A‑12 OXCART as the U-2 spy plane’s successor, intended to meet the nation’s need for a very fast, very high-flying reconnaissance aircraft that could avoid Soviet air defenses.  CIA awarded the OXCART contract to Lockheed (builder of the U-2) in 1959.  In meeting the A‑12’s extreme speed and altitude requirements, Lockheed—led by legendary engineer Clarence “Kelly” Johnson—overcame numerous technical challenges with cutting-edge innovations in titanium fabrication, lubricants, jet engines, fuel, navigation, flight control, electronic countermeasures, radar stealthiness, and pilot life-support systems.  In 1965, after hundreds of hours flown at high personal risk by the elite team of CIA and Lockheed test pilots, the A‑12 was declared fully operational, attaining the design specifications of a sustained speed of Mach 3.2 at 90,000 feet altitude.

CIA’s operational use of the A-12 was beset by not only many technical problems but also political sensitivity to aircraft flights over denied areas and competition from imaging satellites.  After the U-2 piloted by Francis Gary Powers was shot down over the Soviet Union in May 1960, all USSR overflights were halted, thus blocking the A‑12’s original mission to monitor the Soviet Bloc.  By the time of CIA’s first A-12 deployment in 1967, CORONA satellites were being launched regularly to collect thousands of images worldwide each year.  Although its imagery was less timely and of poorer resolution than the A-12’s, CORONA was invulnerable to anti-aircraft missiles and much less provocative than A-12 overflights.  At the same time, the US Air Force was developing the SR‑71, a modified version of the A-12.  Seeing little value in maintaining both overt SR-71 and covert A-12 fleets with similar capabilities, President Johnson ordered retirement of the A‑12 in 1968.

The only A-12 reconnaissance operation, codenamed BLACK SHIELD, took place from May 1967 to May 1968.  A detachment of six pilots and three A-12s based at Kadena Air Base in Okinawa flew 29 missions over East Asia.  The panoramic stereo camera aboard each aircraft yielded considerable high-quality imagery that within hours of landing was processed and under the eyes of photointerpreters, who extracted key intelligence information in support of US military operations during the Vietnam War.

CIA’s A-12 represents a pioneering achievement in aeronautical engineering and, to this day, holds records for speed and altitude (Mach 3.29 at 90,000 feet) for an air-breathing piloted jet aircraft.

In 2007 the US Air Force transferred an A-12 to CIA for display.  CIA Museum’s A-12 is the eighth of 15 built under the OXCART Program and one of nine remaining. It is known as Article 128, with a serial number of 60-6931.  Its first flight was on 3 October 1963, and it was the first of the operational fleet to be certified to fly at Mach 3.  During its lifetime, it logged 453 hours on 232 test and training flights.  The airframe was retired on 28 May 1968.

Article 128 arrived at CIA Headquarters on 9 August 2007 aboard five wide-load trucks. A crew of five assembled the airframe in 10 days, and its official presentation took place on 19 September 2007, as part of CIA’s 60th anniversary celebration.

On 8 December 2007, Article 128 “flew” for the last time when two enormous cranes lifted the 39,000-pound airframe onto its three-pylon mount. The pylons hold the airframe in an operational flight attitude at 85,000-90,000 feet—its nose up 8 degrees and airframe rolled 9 degrees to the left.  Engineering specifications insure that the airframe as mounted could withstand winds of up to 130 mph. As a result, the pylons extend almost 40 feet below the surface where they are anchored into concrete footings.

CIA’s Facilities Support completed the display in early May 2008, 40 years after the OXCART Program ended.  The site also commemorates two CIA A-12 pilots, Walt Ray and Jack Weeks, killed in 1967 and 1968, respectively.  For the CIA workforce, the A-12 is a symbol of the successful collaboration of the Intelligence Community, the Defense Department, and private industry to create a national strategic asset that our adversaries never dreamed possible.

“The A-12 is the pride of the CIA and everyone associated with it, as it should be. You should be proud that the A-12 can be installed in Langley.  We risked our lives and careers daily for the success of the A-12. It was an amazing success due greatly to the CIA management.”

—Colonel Ken Collins, USAF, Ret.
(A-12 Test Pilot, “Dutch 21”;
SR-71 Test Pilot and Instructor Pilot)]]></details>
		<relatedartifacts><![CDATA[]]></relatedartifacts>
		<relatedartifactslinks><![CDATA[]]></relatedartifactslinks>
		<videos><![CDATA[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JXi7LkNipdc&feature=emb_logo]]></videos>
	</node>
	<node>
		<id><![CDATA[9]]></id>
		<link><![CDATA[https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/story/9]]></link>
		<title><![CDATA[CORONA: America’s First Imaging Satellite Program]]></title>
		<details><![CDATA[The 1950s was a time of great uncertainty for the US regarding the Soviet Union's budding strategic nuclear forces.  Although the US knew the Soviets had ambitious programs to develop and deploy intercontinental-range ballistic missiles (ICBMs) and bombers, the US knew little about the scope or success of Soviet efforts.  The US frequently sighted Soviet strategic bombers and had evidence of Soviet missile test programs but lacked the means to get a comprehensive look at overall Soviet strategic deployments—the US did not know how many operational ICBMs and bombers the Soviets had and where they were deployed.  The US Intelligence Community reflected this uncertainty in wild overestimates of Soviet bomber and missile production—the so-called "bomber gap" and "missile gap"—and forecast that the US was falling behind in the nuclear arms race and in real danger of nuclear attack.

Between 1956 and 1960, imagery from 24 U-2 photoreconnaissance aircraft missions over the Soviet Union opened up a crack in the Soviets' armor, but the crack was a small one and it closed before a single ICBM base could be found.   President Eisenhower halted all U‑2 overflights of the USSR when the Soviets shot down an American U-2 and captured its CIA pilot Francis Gary Powers near Sverdlovsk on 1 May 1960.

The CORONA Program began as a joint CIA-Air Force effort in the late 1950s.  Cloaked in secrecy, it was known to the public as a scientific research program named DISCOVERER.  The program’s goals were daunting:  launch a large camera into earth orbit, photograph specific points and areas on the earth’s surface, parachute a capsule of exposed film to earth, snag the capsule in midair over the Pacific Ocean, develop the film, and search the images for answers to the nation’s pressing intelligence questions.  Many things could go wrong—and did.  The first 13 missions failed to return any useable imagery.  Unsuccessful launches, orbits not achieved, camera malfunctions, spacecraft errors, and missed recoveries plagued the program.

Finally, on 18 August 1960, all systems on CORONA Mission XIV operated successfully!  This remarkable technological achievement revolutionized the intelligence world by returning from space more photographic coverage of the Soviet Union in a single mission than in all previous U-2 missions combined.

The first CORONA images were grainy and of limited utility, but quality—and intelligence value—improved rapidly on succeeding missions.  Within a few months, CIA photointerpreters had dispelled both the missile gap and the bomber gap.  They found that Soviets were, in fact, significantly behind the US in development of a workable ICBM and that the Soviets were building up a strategic bomber force but were devoting most of their resources to missile production.  In just a few weeks, CORONA photography had eliminated the Soviet intelligence dilemma that had haunted the US for a decade.

Over the years, the quantity, quality, and reliability of CORONA imagery improved, making it the single most important source of intelligence on Soviet strategic forces:  missile launch complexes and test ranges, ballistic-missile submarine development and deployment, aircraft factories and air bases, anti-ballistic-missile activities, and air defenses.  CORONA was also an invaluable source of intelligence on potential enemies in East Asia, the Middle East, and other areas of interest.  In addition, the US Defense Department used CORONA imagery to produce military maps of denied areas more accurately than ever before.

CORONA enabled the US to specify verifiable terms of the Strategic Arms Limitation Treaty (SALT) with the Soviet Union in 1971.  US negotiators confidently knew that photointerpreters could monitor changes in the size and characteristics of missile launchers, bombers, and submarines.  Satellite imagery became the mainstay of the US arms-control verification process.

CORONA is a milestone in US history.  Developers of this nation’s first film-return photoreconnaissance satellite explored and conquered many technological unknowns of space, lifted the curtain of secrecy that screened military developments within the Soviet Union and Communist China, and opened the way for the even more sophisticated follow-on imaging satellite systems.  The 145th and final CORONA launch took place on 25 May 1972 with the final recovery on 31 May 1972.  Over its lifetime, CORONA provided photographic coverage totaling approximately 750,000,000 square miles of the earth’s surface.  This impressive capability was surpassed only by the quantity and quality of intelligence that it yielded.  Without CORONA, the US may well have been misguidedly pressured into a World War III.]]></details>
		<relatedartifacts><![CDATA[CORONA Film]]></relatedartifacts>
		<relatedartifactslinks><![CDATA[https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/40]]></relatedartifactslinks>
		<videos><![CDATA[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dEkMh54otJ8&feature=emb_logo]]></videos>
	</node>
	<node>
		<id><![CDATA[7]]></id>
		<link><![CDATA[https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/story/7]]></link>
		<title><![CDATA[The Berlin Tunnel]]></title>
		<details><![CDATA[During the Cold War, monitoring the Soviet Union and its influence worldwide was the top priority for the CIA.  In the 1950s, before reconnaissance satellites and other sophisticated collection systems were operational, wiretaps were one of the important technical means for collecting intelligence about Soviet military capabilities.  The challenge was where and how to best conduct such wiretap operations.

Berlin was the center of a vast communications network from France to deep within Russia and Eastern Europe.  At the time, almost all Soviet military telephone and telegraph traffic between Moscow, Warsaw, and Bucharest was routed through Berlin over land lines strung overhead from poles and buried underground.  In a joint effort, the CIA and British Secret Intelligence Service (MI-6) assessed that tapping into underground communication lines in the Soviet sector of Berlin offered a good source for Soviet and East German intelligence.  Tunneling from West Berlin to the underground cables in nearby East Berlin was judged to be feasible and hidden from visual surveillance.

Director of Central Intelligence Allen Dulles approved the covert tunneling and tapping operation in January 1954.  Work began the following month using a US Air Force radar site and warehouse in West Berlin as cover for the construction.

Construction took a year.  Tunnelers removed 3,100 tons of soil (enough to fill 20 average American living rooms) and used 125 tons of steel plate and 1,000 cubic yards of grout.  The finished tunnel was 1,476 feet long.  British technicians installed the taps, and collection began in May 1955.

Unknown at the time to the CIA and MI-6, the KGB—the Soviet Union’s premier intelligence agency—had been aware of the project from its start.  George Blake, a KGB mole inside MI-6, had apprised the Soviets about the secret operation during its planning stages.  But to protect Blake, the KGB allowed the operation to continue until April 1956 when they “accidentally discovered” the tunnel while supposedly repairing faulty underground cables—without putting Blake at risk.  The Soviets planned the discovery in hopes of winning a propaganda victory by publicizing the operation.  But their plan backfired when, instead of condemning the operation, most press coverage marveled at the audacity and technical ingenuity of the operation.

The taps produced enormous amounts of data for almost a year:

50,000 reels of tape
443,000 fully transcribed conversations
40,000 hours of telephone conversations
6,000,000 hours of teletype traffic
1,750 intelligence reports.
Following the tunnel’s shutdown, processing of this immense volume of data took more than two years to complete.

Subsequent studies determined that the Soviets had not attempted to feed false information over the tapped lines—the intelligence that had been collected was genuine.  Despite the KGB’s foreknowledge, CIA ruled this most ambitious operation a success—it yielded valuable intelligence for US policymakers and war fighters, including:

Detailed order of battle and information on activities of Soviet and Warsaw Pact forces
Identification of people working on Soviet atomic energy projects
Early warning of the Soviet’s establishment of an East German army
The poor condition of East German railways
Resentment between Soviets and East Germans
Great tension in Poland
Soviet inaction regarding a military invasion of Western Europe.]]></details>
		<relatedartifacts><![CDATA[]]></relatedartifacts>
		<relatedartifactslinks><![CDATA[]]></relatedartifactslinks>
		<videos><![CDATA[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=W7evqMdo2FI&feature=emb_logo]]></videos>
	</node>
	<node>
		<id><![CDATA[11]]></id>
		<link><![CDATA[https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/story/11]]></link>
		<title><![CDATA[The Office of Strategic Services — America’s First Intelligence Agency]]></title>
		<details><![CDATA[Before World War II, the US Government left the business of collecting and disseminating intelligence to American foreign-policy experts and elements of the armed services.  America’s entry into the war following the intelligence failure of Pearl Harbor led to the establishment of the Office of Strategic Services (OSS) on 13 June 1942.

President Franklin D. Roosevelt appointed William J. Donovan, a highly decorated World War I officer, as Director of the OSS.  Donovan organized the OSS to reflect his vision of a national intelligence center, uniquely combining research and analysis, covert operations, counterintelligence, espionage, and technical development—core missions of today’s Central Intelligence Agency.

Donovan’s Research and Analysis Branch, cornerstone of the OSS, made significant contributions to the Allied victory.  Staffed by some of the best minds in America, the branch provided timely assessment of the Allied bombing campaign in Europe, studied operations in countries where Allied forces were fighting, and developed preparations for the occupation of Germany.  Perhaps most importantly, the branch validated Donovan’s vision of a central all-source analysis capability by demonstrating that the greater part of vital intelligence could be obtained not by parachuting behind enemy lines but by poring through papers, cables, reports, photographs, maps, journals, foreign newspapers, and other materials—laying the foundation of modern intelligence research and analysis.

The OSS formed numerous “Operational Groups” to run American units behind enemy lines.  These were small teams of specially trained US military commandos who fought in uniform with no obvious connection to the OSS (so they would not be shot as spies if captured).  Knowledge of foreign language was essential.  Training included parachuting, amphibious operations, skiing, mountain climbing, radio operation, and espionage tactics.  Operational Groups fought in France, Italy, Greece, Yugoslavia, Burma, Malaya, and China, usually alongside partisan forces.

The OSS joined paramilitary forces from Allied countries to form “Jedburgh” teams that parachuted into France to aid the resistance movement against German occupiers.  A “Jed” team consisted of two to four men:  some combination of an OSS officer, a British officer, a Free French officer or enlisted man, and sometimes a Belgian, Dutch, or Canadian soldier.  More than 90 Jed teams parachuted into France in the summer of 1944 to support the Normandy landings by coordinating airdrops of arms and supplies and by conducting hit-and-run attacks and sabotage raids on the German forces.

OSS’s Detachment 101 served in Burma, recruiting, training, and supporting native Kachin tribesmen to collect intelligence and fight the Japanese occupiers.  When Allied troops invaded Burma in 1944, Detachment 101 teams advanced well ahead of the conventional combat formations, gathering intelligence, sowing rumors, sabotaging key installations, rescuing downed Allied fliers, and snuffing out isolated Japanese positions.

To liberate Thailand from Japanese domination during World War II, the OSS launched the “Free Thai” movement.  The OSS trained the best and brightest volunteer Thai students from universities across the US and dispatched them into Thailand by submarine, seaplane, parachute, and foot.  There they made contact with the resistance, provided accurate intelligence on Japanese military deployments, rescued captured Allied soldiers, and prepared the ground for eventual Japanese surrender.

The best intelligence available to British and American commanders during World War II came from intercepted and deciphered enemy messages obtained through the ULTRA (German) and MAGIC (Japanese) Programs.  In early 1943, Donovan created X-2, an elite counterintelligence branch with access to valuable ULTRA intelligence.  X-2 personnel followed British security practices (more strict than those of other OSS elements) and operated somewhat independently to protect ULTRA.  With this secret intelligence, X-2 guided OSS operations and developed innovative counterintelligence actions.

OSS activities created a steady demand for devices and documents that could be used to trick, attack, or demoralize the enemy.  Donovan capitalized on the many British devices already developed and promoted an in-house capability to adapt them to OSS needs and to fabricate additional ones required for clandestine missions.

The OSS employed nearly 13,000 men and women at its peak and operated for a little more than three years, from 1942 to 1945.  In that short time, it helped shorten the war and save lives in Europe, North Africa, and Asia.  It left a legacy of daring and innovation that has influenced American military and intelligence thinking since World War II.

Today’s Central Intelligence Agency derives a significant institutional and spiritual legacy from the OSS.  In some cases, this legacy descended directly:  key personnel, files, funds, procedures, and contacts assembled by the OSS found their way into the CIA more or less intact.  In other cases, the legacy is less tangible but no less real:  the professionalization of intelligence, the organizational esprit de corps, the essential role of national intelligence in policymaking and war fighting.  The CIA owes a debt of gratitude to the OSS and William J. Donovan, the charismatic leader and moving force behind it.

For videos about OSS, please click here.]]></details>
		<relatedartifacts><![CDATA[Stereoscope and Case
Enigma Machine
William J. Donovan’s Medal of Honor
Office of Strategic Services Letter Removal Device
Office of Strategic Services Patch (Replica)
Office of Strategic Services Pin
Stella Uzdawinis’s Office of Strategic Services Pendant
Office of Strategic Services Escape & Evasion Knife
Office of Strategic Services Compass
William J. Donovan’s Uniform Jacket
Les Marguerites Fleuriront ce Soir
Woodsman’s Pal Knife
Machete
Helms Letter
Irrawaddy Ambush
Eloise Page ID
William J. Donovan’s Garment Bag
Patch of the Free Thai
Paratrooper’s M2 Pocket Knife
Identification Dog Tag
A Psychological Analysis of Adolph Hitler by Walter Langer*
Counterfeit Nazi Stamp
Mark IV Radio
OSS Identification Badge #2923
British Army Pocket Knife
Bolo Knife with Leather Sheath
US Army Signal Corps “Handie-Talkie”
Letter from President Harry S. Truman to William J. Donovan
OSS Field Compass
China-Burma-India Theater Patch
OSS Officer William H. Pietsch, Jr., Mentioned in Dispatch from King George VI
OSS Wax Seal Embosser
Sidearm Knife and Sheath
Forged German Passport
Forged French Passport
OSS Job Register
$20 Gold Coin Minted in 1858
Uniform of OSS Col. William H. Pietsch, Jr.
Plate from Hitler’s Chancellery
Metal Cuspidor]]></relatedartifacts>
		<relatedartifactslinks><![CDATA[https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/44

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/67

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/72

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/73

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/74

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/75

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/76

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/78

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/80

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/82

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/107

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/134

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/135

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/139

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/142

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/161

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/188

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/189

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/190

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/191

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/206

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/207

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/208

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/209

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/210

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/211

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/212

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/213

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/214

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/215

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/216

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/217

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/218

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/219

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/220

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/221

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/222

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/223

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/224

https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/cia-museum/experience-the-collection/index.html#!/artifact/225]]></relatedartifactslinks>
		<videos><![CDATA[https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLE6F88ABB81C68527]]></videos>
	</node>
</data>
